Guide to the Frank Herbst Papers and Photographs WAG.201
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Frank Herbst Papers and Photographs
1937-1993
1941-1957
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Herbst, Frank, 1917-1979
WAG.201
0.5 Linear Feet in 10 folders in 2 shared boxes.
Frank Herbst was a union leader who worked for the State, County and Municipal Workers Union Local 1 as a manager and business agent in the 1940's and 1950's. Under Herbst the Local achieved gains in wages, working conditions, staff promotions and grievance procedures. Herbst was called before the House Un-American Activities Committee as Local 1 came under McCarthyite criticism. In 1952 Herbst had to leave Local 1 in order for the union to maintain official recognition and continue its representation of the workers. The local eventually merged with Teamsters Local 237. The collection contains Herbst's HUAC testimony, as well as statements and fliers from Teamsters Local 237. Photocopies of three scrapbooks Herbst kept though the 1940s and 1950s contain information on Herbst, Local 1 and anticommunism. Materials pertaining the "Pillar of Labor" tribute to Herbst include biographical information and a compilation of Herbst's columns for Local 1's newsletter, the Welfare Reporter. Approxmiately fifteen black and white photographs document Herbst's student organizing, wartime service and United Public Workers conventions and meetings.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains Herbst's HUAC testimony, as well as statements and fliers from Teamsters Local 237. Photocopies of three scrapbooks Herbst kept though the 1940s and 1950s contain information on Herbst, Local 1 and anticommunism. Materials pertaining the "Pillar of Labor" tribute to Herbst include biographical information and a compilation of Herbst's columns for Local 1's newsletter, the Welfare Reporter. Approxmiately fifteen black and white photographs document Herbst's student organizing and wartime service as well as United Public Workers conventions and meetings.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in repository; provenance is unknown. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1993.003 and 1993.008.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Related Archival Materials
WAG 199 United Public Workers of America: Reserach Files
TAM 533 Investigation Files of the Rapp-Coudert Committee
Historical/Biographical Note
Frank Herbst was born in 1917 in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn and attended New York City public schools. He graduated from City College in 1938 with a Bachelor of Business Administration. While a student, he became active in campus politics. He was elected president of the Student Council as well as president of the City College Chapter of the American Student Union. After graduation, he found work as a case worker with the New York City Department of Welfare (later the Human Resources Administration). He joined the State, County and Municipal Workers Union, Local 1 and became the manager of the Local.
The outbreak of World War II interrupted Herbst's union work. He enlisted in the Navy and spent three years as a Quartermaster First Class and Assistant Navigator on a destroyer escort. After discharge in 1946, he returned to the union and accepted the position of Local 1 Representative (business agent), which through merger became part of the United Public Workers of America. Under his leadership, the Local achieved significant gains in wages, working conditions, staff promotions and grievance procedures, as well as in services to the Welfare clients. Herbst was a regular columnist in Welfare Reporter, the newsletter of Local 1.
In 1950, the CIO forced out the United Public Workers of America and other national unions as "communist-dominated". Herbst himself was called in front of the House Un-American Activities Committee. He left the local in 1952 in order to enable the union maintain official recognition and continue to represent the workers. The remnants of the Local merged with Teamsters Local 237. In the early 1970s Herbst became a key figure in the planning and construction of the 1199 Plaza housing development. He died in 1979.
Municipal officials and employees |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; College students -- Political activity -- New York (State) -- New York.; Photographs.; Anti-fascist movements -- United States.; Scrapbooks.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Organizing.; Testimonies.; Clippings (information artifacts); Reports.; New York (N.Y.).; Anti-communist movements |z New York (State) |z New York.; American Student Union; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities; New York (State). Legislature. Joint Legislative Committee to Investigate the Educational System of the State of New York; United Public Workers of America; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America. Local 237 (New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Human Resources Administration; City University of New York. City College; 1199, National Health and Human Service Employees Union
- "Pillar of Labor" Memorial, 1993 (Box Tamiment Shared A005, Folder 1)
- International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 237, undated (Box Tamiment Shared A005, Folder 2)
- Oversize Portraits (Photographs), circa 1954-1955 (Box Tamiment Shared MSOS005, Folder 1)
- Portraits (Photographs), 1937-1953, undated (Box Tamiment Shared A005, Folder 3)
- Scrapbook I, 1937-1948 (Box Tamiment Shared MSOS005, Folder 2)
- Scrapbook II, 1949-1957 (Box Tamiment Shared MSOS005, Folder 3)
- Scrapbook III, 1947-1948, undated (Box Tamiment Shared MSOS005, Folder 4)
- Testimony regarding Communist Activity (Rapp-Coudert Committee, House Un-American Activities Committee), 1941-1948, undated (Box Tamiment Shared A005, Folder 4)
- United Public Workers: Conventions and Meetings (Photographs), 1946-1949, undated (Box Tamiment Shared A005, Folder 5)
- Wartime Service (Photographs), 1943 (Box Tamiment Shared A005, Folder 6)